Christensen, C. Roland (Carl Roland), 1919-1999. C. Roland Christensen Papers, 1931-1998: A Finding Aid
C. Roland Christensen papers, 1931-1998
- II. HBS Teaching Records, 1931-1998
  - Subseries G. Teaching About Teaching, 1931-1998
    - iv. General, 1931-1998
      - "Teaching and the Case Method" and "Teaching and the Case Method: Instructor's Guide" draft material, undated; 001347577_FD_0001-0004, 0021-0022, 0024-0031, 0034-0039, 0041-0055
      - Teaching Notes and Readings (Disbound Volume), circa 1940s-1980s (Box 68, f. 2-7)
      - History of the Harvard Business School, 1947-1985 (Box 68, f. 8-9)
      - Ian Cumming, circa 1950-1994 (Box 68, f. 10)
      - Problems and Processes of Field Research, 1953-circa1990s (Box 68, f. 11)
      - Pierre R. Goetschin, 1958-1996 (Box 68, f. 12)
      - "Preparation for the Profession", John Ellis, 1960 (Box 68, f. 13)
      - Miscellaneous Publications, 1962-1997 (Box 69, f. 1)
      - General Management, 1963-1979 (Box 69, f. 2)
      - Notes on Teaching, 1965-1995 (Box 69, f. 3)
      - A Stages of Development Model and its Proposed Role in Business Policy II, Bruce Scott, circa 1966 (Box 69, f. 4)
      - Notes on Administrative Action, 1969 (Box 69, f. 5)
      - Teaching Notes, 1969-1990 (Box 69, f. 6)
      - Ian Cumming, Leucadia, 1970-1989 (Box 69, f. 7)
      - Tombstones for Section Discussion Leaders, circa 1971-1972 (Box 69, f. 8)
      - "Teachers Also Must Learn", 1975-1977 (Box 69, f. 9)
      - Questioning, 1977-1982 (Box 69, f. 10)
      - Discussion Learning and Teaching, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 69, f. 11)
      - Grading, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 69, f. 12)
      - Observation, Notes/Exercises, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 69, f. 13)
      - Summary Notes, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 69, f. 14)
      - "Case Preparation - A Guide for Research Assistants at HBS", Penny Pittman Merliss, 1981 (Box 69, f. 15)
      - Questioning, circa 1981-1987 (Box 69, f. 16)
      - "Note on the Lifecycle of Section I; The First Year of the MBA Program", C. R. Christensen/Abby Hansen, 1982 (Box 69, f. 17)
      - Society of Teachers, 1983 (Box 69, f. 18)
      - Society of Teachers, 1983-1986 (Box 69, f. 19)
      - Good Cases - Good Discussion, 1984-1991 (Box 69, f. 20)
      - "A Study of the Academic Environment at the Harvard Business School: Summary Findings", Elaine Klein, May 1985 (Box 69, f. 21)
      - Alumni Day, May 31, 1985 (Box 69, f. 22)
      - Feedback, 1986 (Box 70, f. 1)
      - "Education for Judgment", Reviews, 1986-1992 (Box 70, f. 2)
      - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1986 (Box 70, f. 3)
      - Precis: Education for Judgment, circa 1980s (Box 70, f. 4-7)
      - "Education for Judgment" draft material, 001347577_FD_0005, 0010, 0019-0020
      - Print material accompanying item 001347577_FD_0019 (Box 79, f. 10)
      - HBS Success, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 70, f. 8-9)
      - Improving Teaching and Learning, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 70, f. 10)
      - Miscellaneous Copies of Publications, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 70, f. 11)
      - "Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain", Betty Edwards, 1989-1997 (Box 70, f. 12)
      - Stanford Report, April 5, 1990 (Box 70, f. 13)
      - "The Improvement of Teaching" January 2, 1991 (Box 70, f. 14)
      - "Education for Judgment" Mailing, 1991-1996 (Box 70, f. 15)
      - "The Elements of Case Development: A Practitioner's Guide", Abby J. Hansen, 1992 (Box 70, f. 16)
      - Correspondence and Permission, "Teaching and the Case Method", 1992-1998 (Box 71, f. 1-3)
      - The University of Utah, circa 1993 (Box 71, f. 4)
      - Observation, March 1994 (Box 71, f. 5)
      - Distribution - "Teaching and the Case Method", 3rd Ed., 1994 (Box 71, f. 6)
      - Endorsements - "Teaching and the Case Method", 3rd Ed., 1994 (Box 71, f. 7)
      - Observation - Publications, 1994 (Box 71, f. 8)
      - The University of Utah, 1994 (Box 71, f. 9-10)
      - The University of Utah, National Advisory Council, circa 1994 (Box 71, f. 11)
      - Early Warnings/Or Seven Warning Signs Trouble is Ahead, 1995 (Box 71, f. 12)
      - Miscellaneous Publications, 1995-1998 (Box 71, f. 13)
      - Observation Planning, 1996 (Box 71, f. 14-15)
      - Bok Center, Spring 1996 (Box 71, f. 16)
      - Summary, Reflections on Teaching, 1996 (Box 72, f. 1)
      - Al Bartovics, Baker Library, 1997 (Box 72, f. 2)
      - Boston College Graduate School of Management MBA Viewbook, 1997 (Box 72, f. 3)
      - Handouts, "4 Important Things for New Teachers", 1997 (Box 72, f. 4)
      - HBS Fund for Compassionate Support, 1997 (Box 72, f. 5)
      - "Writing Cases for Teaching", Abby J. Hansen, 1997 (Box 72, f. 6)
      - Harvard Macy Institute Strategic Planning Meeting, December 19, 1997 (Box 72, f. 7)
      - Classroom Observation, circa 1990s (Box 72, f. 8)
      - Directional Techniques, Summary, undated (Box 72, f. 9)
      - First Day of Class, undated (Box 72, f. 10)
      - Laura Linard, Historical Collections, undated (Box 72, f. 11)
      - The New Instructor, undated (Box 72, f. 12)
      - Operational Guidelines, Carlson, undated (Box 72, f. 13)
      - Process Comments, undated (Box 72, f. 14)
      - Suggestions for New Teachers, undated (Box 72, f. 15)
      - Wheelock, undated (Box 72, f. 16)
      - Correspondence Regarding Writings and Drafts of Various Publications, circa 1990s (Box 72, f. 17)
      - Draft material relating to teaching and class discussion, undated; 001347577_FD_0006-0007, 0009, 0012, 0014-0016
      - Print material accompanying item 001347577_FD_0012 (Box 79, f. 7)
      - Print material accompanying item 001347577_FD_0015 (Box 79, f. 8)
- III. Research, Writings and Speeches, 1946-1996
  This series consists of articles and speeches by Christensen as well as various publications not authored by Christensen that he separately maintained as "Article Files". This series also contains digital content of Christensen's Class if 1963 Reunion speech and articles written by Christensen relating to discussion-based teaching.
  - Subseries A. Writings and Speeches, 1960-1996
    This subseries includes an article published by Christensen in 1960 and speeches made by him between 1963 and 1996. Many of the speeches are concerned with the nature of teaching and the possibilities of improving instruction by the case method. This subseries also contains digital content of Christensen's Class if 1963 Reunion speech.
    The materials are arranged chronologically.
    - "We Stand on Shifting Ground", HBS Bulletin, December 1960 (Box 72, f. 18)
    - Speeches, 1963-1989 (Box 72, f. 19-20)
    - HBSA Executive Council Speech, October 21, 1983 (Box 72, f. 21)
    - Speech, HBS Visiting Committee, 1983-1986 (Box 72, f. 22)
    - Speech, Associated Harvard Alumni Group, March 9, 1985 (Box 72, f. 23-24)
    - Speech, Babson College Commencement Address, May 18, 1985 (Box 72, f. 25)
    - IMEDE Presentation, May 17, 1987 (Box 72, f. 26)
    - Speech, Academy of Management, August 9, 1987 (Box 73, f. 1)
    - Doctoral Convocation, June 1988 (Box 73, f. 2)
    - Alumni Council Speech, June 2, 1988 (Box 73, f. 3)
    - Remarks to the Class of 1963, July 19, 1988 (Box 73, f. 4)
    - Class of 1963 Reunion Speech, September 30, 1988 (Box 73, f. 5)
    - Class of 1963 Reunion Speech, undated; 001347577_FD_0017
    - Print material accompanying item 001347577_FD_0017 (Box 79, f. 9)
    - IMEDE, Dedication of the Bignami Building, May 26, 1989 (Box 73, f. 6)
    - Speech, Florida International University, March 19, 1992 (Box 73, f. 7)
    - Overseer's Meeting, Professional Education, Babson, April 5, 1992 (Box 73, f. 8)
    - The University of Utah, Harvard Alumni Speech, May 13, 1994 (Box 73, f. 9)
    - The University of Utah, Speeches, 1994 (Box 73, f. 10-13)
    - Toasts, 1994-1996 (Box 73, f. 14)
    - Introduction, Sarah James, n.d. (Box 73, f. 15)
    - Draft articles on discussion-based teaching, undated; 001347577_FD_0032-0033
  - Subseries B. Article Files, 1946-1974
    Christensen separately maintained this group of publications as his Article Files. Article topics include policy studies, management training, leadership and the social sciences.
    The Article Files were added to the collection in 2007.
    The articles are arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Archibald, K.A. "Three Views of the Expert's Role in Policymaking", 1970 (Box 73, f. 16)
    - Bauer, Raymond A. "Decision-making: An Intellectual Process or a Social Process?", 1959 (Box 73, f. 17)
    - Bauer, Raymond A. "The Role of Information in the Policy Process" (Draft Proposal for a Research Program), 1965 (Box 73, f. 18)
    - Bauer, Raymond A. "Social Psychology and the Study of Policy Formation", 1965 (Box 74, f. 1)
    - Berle, Adolf A. "Second Edition/Corporate Power", 1969 (Box 74, f. 2)
    - Berle, A.A. "Economic Power and the Free Society", 1957 (Box 74, f. 3)
    - Bernstein, Leonard "The Principle of Hope" 4-374-041, 1970 (Box 74, f. 4)
    - Bliss, Charles A. "Absolutism in the Realm of Uncertainty", 1969 (Box 74, f. 5)
    - Bok, Enid Curtis "The State of the Art in Policy Studies", 1964 (Box 74, f. 6)
    - Bowen, Howard R. "A Game of Numbers", 1962 (Box 74, f. 7)
    - Bryson, Lyman "Notes on a Theory of Advice", 1951 (Box 74, f. 8)
    - Bundy, McGeorge "Damn the Absolute" Notes on Authority and Autonomy, 1970 (Box 74, f. 9)
    - Clerk, Joseph Porter, Jr. "The Culture of Bureaucracy: The Art of the Memorandum", 1969 (Box 74, f. 10)
    - The Consultant Role and Organizational Leadership: Improving Human Relations in Industry, 1948 (Box 74, f. 11)
    - Dewey, John "Social Thought and Belief as Experimental", 1946 (Box 74, f. 12)
    - Dror, Yehezkel "Muddling Through -'Science' or Inertia?", 1964 (Box 74, f. 13)
    - Erikson, Erik H. "The Nature of Clinical Evidence", 1958 (Box 74, f. 14)
    - Evans, Richard L. "The Courage to Carry Responsibility", 1956 (Box 74, f. 15)
    - Finklestein, Louis "The Businessman's Moral Failure", 1958 (Box 74, f. 16)
    - Foell, Earl W. "Having eyes--and seeing", April 5 1965 (Box 74, f. 17)
    - Gouldner, Alvin W. "Some Theoretical Requirements of the Applied Social Sciences", n.d. (Box 74, f. 18)
    - Grace, Harry A. "The First Stage of Inquiry", 1963 (Box 74, f. 19)
    - Heany, Donald F. "Is TIMS Talking to Itself?", 1965 (Box 74, f. 20)
    - Hendrickson, Roy F. "The Administrative Generalist", 1955 (Box 74, f. 21)
    - Hoffmann, Banesh "The College Boards Fail the Test", 1965 (Box 74, f. 22)
    - Ickis, John Cather "Pitfalls in the Implementation of Change", 1974 (Box 74, f. 23)
    - Kelly, George A. "Man's Construction of his Alternatives", circa 1950s (Box 74, f. 24)
    - Kerr, Clark "The Frantic Race to Remain Contemporary", 1964 (Box 74, f. 25)
    - Laski, Harold J. "The Limitations of the Expert", 1946 (Box 74, f. 26)
    - Livingston, J. Sterling "Myth of the Well-Educated Manager", 1971 (Box 74, f. 27)
    - Lindblom, Charles E. "The Policy-Making Process", 1968 (Box 74, f. 28)
    - Lindblom, C.E. "The Science of Muddling Through", 1959 (Box 74, f. 29)
    - Litchfield, Edward H. "Notes on a General Theory of Administration", 1956 (Box 75, f. 1)
    - Myers, Ann D. "An Inquiry: The Function of Religion in Society", 1971-1972 (Box 75, f. 2)
    - MacLeish, Archibald "Why Do We Teach Poetry?", 1973 (Box 75, f. 3)
    - Mason, Edward S. "The Apologetics of 'Managerialism'", 1958 (Box 75, f. 4)
    - Peterson, Harold "The Wizard Who Oversimplified: A Fable", 1965 (Box 75, f. 5)
    - Pfiffner, John M. "Administrative Rationality", 1960 (Box 75, f. 6)
    - "Public Administration as Process", undated (Box 75, f. 7)
    - Reagan, Michael D. "Policy Issues: The Interaction of Substance and Process", 1967 (Box 75, f. 8)
    - Saltonstall, William G. "Father and Son: An Inquiry into the Nature of Teaching" (The Phillips Exeter Bulletin), 1962 (Box 75, f. 9)
    - Scharpf, Fritz "Policy Sciences Teaching in Context: A Note on Germany", 1970 (Box 75, f. 10)
    - Schein, Edgar H. "The Problem of Moral Education for the Business Manager" (Industrial Mgt. Review, Sloan School of Management, MIT), Fall 1966 (Box 75, f. 11)
    - Scott, Bruce R. "Stages of Corporate Development: A Descriptive Model", 1968 (Box 75, f. 12)
    - Scott, Bruce R. "Exercise on Strategy, Measurement and Reward", undated (Box 75, f. 13)
    - Simon, Herbert A. "The Business School, A Problem in Organizational Design", 1967 (Box 75, f. 14)
    - Siu, Ralph G.H. "Work and Serenity", undated (Box 75, f. 15)
    - Tilles, S. "How to Think About Using a Consultant", undated (Box 75, f. 16)
    - Tilles, Dr. Seymour "Marketing Strategy Explicit", circa 1966 (Box 75, f. 17)
    - Tilles, Dr. Seymour (& Contas, Arthur P.) "Planning in the Family Firm", 1965 (Box 75, f. 18)
    - Tilles, Seymour "Survival Strategies for Family Firms", 1970 (Box 75, f. 19)
    - Vickers, Geoffrey "The Psychology of Policy Making and Social Change", 1963 (Box 75, f. 20)
- Series IV. HBS Administrative Files, 1946-1970
  The series is comprised of one restricted subseries: Administrative and Academic Planning Files; and one open subseries: MBA Review Committee Files. The Administrative and Academic Planning Files consist of materials formerly kept in looseleaf binders, arranged, for the most part, according to academic year. The bulk of the subseries concerns the teaching of Business Policy and planning for the administration of Business Policy courses between 1950 and 1970. Included are correspondence about programs, handwritten notes by Christensen, memos and guidelines, course outlines, reports, exams, course evaluations, and other materials. A smaller amount of similar files for Administrative Policy, 1946-1957, is also included. The MBA Review Committee Files consist of memos, reports, handwritten notes by Christensen, and related documents from 1959-1961. The main thrust of the Committee's work was to create a strategic plan for an improved future MBA program at HBS.
  - Subseries A. Administrative and Academic Planning Files, 1946-1970
    Restricted until 2020. Folder titles have been redacted.
  - Subseries B. MBA Review Committee Files, 1959-1961
    - MBA Study Committee, undated (Box 79, f. 1)
    - MBA Study Committee, 1959 (Box 79, f. 2)
    - MBA Study Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 79, f. 3-4)
    - MBA Study Committee, minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 79, f. 5)
    - MBA Study Committee, report, 1961 (Box 79, f. 6)
- Series V. Audiovisual Records, 1982-1997
  The series consists of audio cassettes, CDs, and a transcription of Christensen being interviewed by Albert Bartovics and Carole Foster (of Baker Library, Historical Collections) about the development of Business Policy cases and their uses at HBS. The recordings were made at Christensen’s Lexington, Massachusetts, residence in September 1997. Additional recordings, including Christensen's talks at the Cotting Library in 1982, an interview with Bob Eccles in 1988 and a videorecording entitled "Case Video to Accompany Business Policy Text and Cases" featuring Christensen, are also included.
  The additional audio recordings were added to the collection in 2007.
  Restricted until reformatted.
  - Christensen, Cotting Library, February 18, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Christensen, Cotting Library, February 24, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Christensen, Cotting Library, March 3, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Christensen, Cotting Library, March 10, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Christensen [Cotting Library?], March 17, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Christensen, Cotting Library, March 24, 1982 (1 audio cassette) (Box 80)
  - Round Table, April 23, 1986 (2 audio cassettes) (Box 80)
  - Christensen/Bob Eccles Interview, May 13, 1988 (2 audio cassettes) (Box 80)
  - Christensen/Al Bartovics/Carole Foster Interview, September 1997 (2 sets of 2 audio cassettes) (Box 80)
  - "Academe's Quiet Revolution: Universities Rediscover Teaching", n.d. (2 audio cassettes) (Box 80)
  - Christensen/Al Bartovics/Carole Foster Interview, September 1997 (2 CDs) (Box 81)
  - Christensen/Al Bartovics/Carole Foster Interview Transcription, September 1997 (Box 81)
  - "Case Video to Accompany Business Policy Text and Cases", 7th Ed., Bower/Bartlett/Christensen/Pearson/Andrews, 1991 (1 videocassette) (Box 81)
SEPARATION RECORD
The following items have been removed from the collection and have been separately cataloged:
Barnes, Louis B. et al. Teaching and the Case Method: Text, Cases and Readings, (3rd Ed.). Boston: Harvard Business School Press, 1994.
Barnes, Louis B. et al. Teaching and the Case Method: Instructor's Guide, (3rd Ed.). Boston: Harvard Business School Press, 1994.
Christensen, C. Roland et al. Instructor's Manual to Accompany Policy Formulation and Administration, (9th Ed.). Homewood, IL: R. D. Irwin, 1985.
Gullette, Margaret M. (Ed.). The Art and Craft of Teaching. Cambridge, MA: Harvard-Danforth Center for Teaching and Learning, 1982.